Inventory of the Herbert H. Bateman Papers, 1946-1982, 1968-1982
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Herbert H. Bateman Papers, 1946-1982, 1968-1982.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 83 B31
12,731 items.
Office files, 1968-1982, of Herbert H. Bateman, Virginia Republican State Senator from Newport News.
Herbert H. Bateman,; John N. Dalton,; Mills E. (Mills Edwin) Godwin,; A. Linwood (Abner Linwood) Holton,; Charles S. Robb.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: Acc. no. 83-1; 12,731 items, 1/20/1983.
Biographical/Historical Information
Herbert Harvell Bateman was born in Perquimans County, North Carolina, 7 August 1928. He graduated from the College of William and Mary and received his law degree from Georgetown University. He served in the Virginia Senate from 1968 until 1983 when he was elected to Congress.
Biography Timeline
1928 August 7 Born, Elizabeth City, North Carolina
1949 Graduated from the College of William and Mary
1951- 1953 Served in the U.S. Air Force
1954 May 29 Married Laura Yacob
1956 [?] Law degree from Georgetown University Law Center
1968 Elected to Virginia State Senate
1976 Changed political affiliation from Democratic to Republican
1982 Elected to U.S. Congress
Committee Service State Senate
Standing Committees
1968- 1982 Courts of Justice
1968-1982 Finance
1968- 1971 Enrolled Bills
1968-1971 Fish & Game
1972-1976 Agriculture, Conservation and Natural Resources (Chaired)
1972-1982 Transportation
1977-1982 Rehabilitation and Social Services
Study Commissions
1968-1971 Court System Study
1968 State Aid to Public Schools
1970-1973 Consumer Credit
1971 Narcotics and Drug Laws
1973 Public School Financing
1973-1975 Milk Commission Study
1973-1982 Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission [JLARC]
1975-1977 Coastal Study
1976 Products Liability
1978-1980 Sentencing
1978 Obscenity and Pornography
1978 Highway Maintenance
1979 Highway Funds Allocation
1978 Telephone Companies, Interstate Toll and Service Revenue
1978-1980 Virginia Individual Income Structure
1979 Railways, The Hazards Posed by Debris
1979-1982 Coal and Energy Commission
1980 Taxation of Leasehold Interests
1980; 1982 Virginia Independence Bicentennial
1981 Divorce Settlements
1982 JLARC-Review of General Government
1982 Fuller Road Ownership
Scope and Content Information
Office files, 1968-1982, of Herbert H. Bateman, Virginia Republican State Senator from Newport News. Includes correspondence with constituents and state officials; bills and legislative materials; memoranda; reports; pamphlets; and publications arranged according to subject. The collection contains background information and committee working papers showing Virginia's responses to the energy crisis of the late 1970's and to Ronald Reagan's "New Federalism" programs as well as the state's policies on education, transportation, and welfare funding, and the activities of state regulatory agencies.
There are materials concerning Bateman's sponsorship of coastal zone land management bills, bills for execution by lethal injection, bills for mandatory sentencing by judges in criminal cases and his activities on behalf of the port of Newport News, the Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company and the Virginia seafood industry. The largest body of material concerns Bateman's 1975-1977 efforts as paid counsel and as senator to minimize the economic impact of the poisoning of the James River by kepone on the Virginia seafood industry.
Prominent correspondents include Linwood Holton, Mills Godwin, John Dalton, Charles Robb, Harry F. Byrd, Jr., William Spong, Thomas Downing, William Scott and Paul Trible, other General Assembly members and state agency commissioners.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection is organized into the following 249 series:
Series 1: Abortion
Series 2: Adult (Nursing) Homes
Series 3: Air Pollution
Series 4: Artificial Insemination
Series 5: Asbestos
Series 6: Attorney General Opinions
Series 7: Auto Clubs
Series 8: Auto Inspections
Series 9: Banking Legislation
Series 10: Bankruptcy Bill
Series 11: Bingo
Series 12: Biomass
Series 13: Budget
Series 14: Busing
Series 15: Capital Punishment
Series 16: Christopher Newport College
Series 17: Child Auto Safety
Series 18: Claims Subcommittee, 1982
Series 19: Coal Tax
Series 20: Coal and Energy Commission, 1979- 1982
Series 21: Coastal Zone Land Management Act
Series 22: Coastal Zone Land Management Bill
Series 23: Commendations
Series 24: Conflict of Interest
Series 25: Consolidation
Series 26: Constitutional Offices
Series 27: Consumer Credit
Series 28: Consumer Protection
Series 29: Corrections
Series 30: Court System
Series 31: Courts of Justice
Series 32: Covenant Not to Sue
Series 33: Credit Life Insurance
Series 34: Daily Press Essay
Series 35: District of Columbia Statehood
Series 36: Divorce Laws
Series 37: Domestic Relations Law
Series 38: Drunk Driving
Series 39: Economic Data
Series 40: Education, Public
Series 41: Education Association of Newport News
Series 42: Educational Issues, 1982
Series 43: Elderly
Series 44: Election Disputes
Series 45: Election Laws
Series 46: Election Returns
Series 47: Environment
Series 48: Environmental Protection Agency
Series 49: Execution Bill
Series 50: Farley, Guy
Series 51: Farm Bureau
Series 52: Federal Block Grants/Funding Reductions
Series 53: Federal Impact Aid
Series 54: Finance Committee, 1980-1982
Series 55: Fishing Licensing
Series 56: Food Act (Virginia), 1978
Series 57: Freedom of Information Act
Series 58: Fuel Conversion Authority
Series 59: Game Warden Bill
Series 60: Garnett, Henry D.
Series 61: Garnishing Legislation
Series 62: Gas Tax
Series 63: Gasohol
Series 64: General Assembly Summary, 1981
Series 65: Government Competition
Series 66: Government Reorganization
Series 67: Gun Control
Series 68: Habitual Offenders Act
Series 69: Higher Education
Series 70: Highway Appropriations, 1981-1982
Series 71: Highway Department Study
Series 72: Highway Funds
Series 73: Holidays, State
Series 74: Homes for Adults
Series 75: Homes for the Aged
Series 76: Homebuilders
Series 77: Housing Bills
Series 78: Human Resources
Series 79: In Vitro Clinic
Series 80: Income Sur Tax
Series 81: Industrial Revenue Bonds
Series 82: Insurance
Series 83: Interest Rate Legislation
Series 84: Intermediate Appellate Court
Series 85: Interstate 664
Series 86: Joint Legislative Audit & Review Commission (JLARC)
Series 87: Joint Subcommittee to Study Virginia's Individual Income Tax Structure
Series 88: Judicial Nominations
Series 89: Juvenile Courts
Series 90: Juvenile Judges--Authority of
Series 91: Juvenile Justices
Series 92: Juvenile Justice Code
Series 93: Kepone
Series 94: Kindergarten
Series 95: Labor Laws
Series 96: Laetrile
Series 97: Land Surveyors
Series 98: Law Enforcement Training
Series 99: League of Women Voters
Series 100: Leasehold Interest--Joint Subcommittee
Series 101: Legislative Aides
Series 102: Legislative Process
Series 103: Legislative Proposals, 1980-1982
Series 104: Limitations on Spending
Series 105: Litter Laws
Series 106: Lobbyists
Series 107: Local Revenue Sources
Series 108: Lottery
Series 109: Manufactured Housing Association
Series 110: Marine Resources Management
Series 111: Medical Lien
Series 112: Medical Malpractice
Series 113: Medicaid and Health Issues
Series 114: Medicaid Cost Containment
Series 115: Mental Health
Series 116: Metro
Series 117: Milk Commission
Series 118: National Conference of State Legislatures, Urban Development Committee
Series 119: Nature Conservancy
Series 120: Newport News Bar Association
Series 121: Newport News, City of
Series 122: Newport News Development
Series 123: Newport News Downtown
Series 124: Newport News Public Education
Series 125: Newport News Shipbuilding
Series 126: No-Fault Insurance
Series 127: Obenshain Campaign
Series 128: Obscenity
Series 129: Occupational Safety
Series 130: Occupational Therapists
Series 131: Oil Refinery
Series 132: Old Dominion University
Series 133: Operator's Licensing
Series 134: Optometrist Legislation
Series 135: Parental Support Bill
Series 136: Pan-Mutual Betting
Series 137: Parole
Series 138: Patrick Henry Hospital
Series 139: Peninsula Airport Commission
Series 140: Peninsula Catholic Scholarship Fund
Series 141: Peninsula Economic Development Council
Series 142: Peninsula Nature and Science Center
Series 143: Peninsula Shipbuilders Association
Series 144: Pentran
Series 145: Prenatal Care
Series 146: Pine Haven Home for Adults
Series 147: Ports of Virginia
Series 148: Post-Session, 1976, 1978-1980, 1982
Series 149: Pre-Filed Bills, 1980
Series 150: Pre-Sessions, 1980&1981
Series 151: Privileges and Elections Committee
Series 152: Procurement Bill
Series 153: Products Liability
Series 154: Proposition 13
Series 155: Public Employees
Series 156: Public Employees-Collective Bargaining
Series 157: Radioactive Materials
Series 158: Reapportionment
Series 159: Recommendations
Series 160: Rehabilitation and Social Services
Series 161: Rebublican Caucus
Series 162: Retirement
Series 163: Richmond Waterfront Terminals
Series 164: Right to Work Law
Series 165: Sales Tax on Vending Machines
Series 166: Sales Tax Regulations
Series 167: Savings and Loan Legislation
Series 168: School Distribution Formula
Series 169: Seafood Industry
Series 170: Seafood Products Commission
Series 171: Sea Grant Consortium
Series 172: Seat Belt Legislation
Series 173: Senate Bills, 1981-1982
Series 174: Senate Committees
Series 175: Senate Joint Resolution 24 (S.J.Res. 24)
Series 176: Senate Rules
Series 177: Sentencing
Series 178: Service Life Extension Program
Series 179: Sexual Assault
Series 180: Sex Education
Series 181: Soft Drink Tax
Series 182: Southern Legislative Conference
Series 183: Special Education
Series 184: Spending Limit Proposal
Series 185: Spouse Abuse
Series 186: State Water Control Board
Series 187: Taxation
Series 188: Taxation Procedures
Series 189: Taxation Expenditures
Series 190: Taxation of Corporate Income
Series 191: Tax Relief for the Elderly
Series 192: Thomas Nelson Community College
Series 193: Tidewater Caucus
Series 194: Time-Share Legislation
Series 195: Tobacco Conventions
Series 196: Tort Claims Act
Series 197: Toxic Substances
Series 198: Toxic Substances Act
Series 199: Transportation
Series 200: Transportation- Northern Virginia
Series 201: Transportation Subcommittee
Series 202: Transportation Department Study
Series 203: Trible
Series 204: Trucks
Series 205: Tuition Assistance Program
Series 206: Unemployment Compensation
Series 207: United Way Campaign
Series 208: Uranium Mining
Series 209: Urban Development
Series 210: Vending Machine Taxes
Series 211: Veterans
Series 212: Virginia Educational Loan Authority (VELA)
Series 213: Virginia Electric and Power Company (VEPCO)
Series 214: Virginia Evaluation Act
Series 215: Virginia Housing and Development Authority (VHDA)
Series 216: Virginia Institute of Marine Science (VIMS)
Series 217: Virginia Municipal League
Series 218: Virginia Oil and Gas Authority
Series 219: Virginia Port Authority
Series 220: Virginia State School
Series 221: Wage Assignment in Support Cases
Series 222: Water Resources
Series 223: Water Resources: Bi-State Commission
Series 224: Water Resources: Potomac
Series 225: Watercraft Sales and Use Tax
Series 226: Welfare and Institutions
Series 227: Welfare for the Elderly
Series 228: Welfare Study Commission
Series 229: Western State Hospital
Series 230: Wetlands
Series 231: Wetlands Bills
Series 232: William and Mary, The College of (W&M)
Series 233: Wine Dealers' Franchise
Series 234: Yorktown, Town of
Series 235: Zoning
Series 236: Research Materials
Series 237: Constituent Correspondence
Series 238: Constituent Correspondence Form Letters
Series 239: Legislative Correspondence
Series 240: 1982 Session-Communications from Governor, et al.
Series 241: 1982 Session-Constituent Problems
Series 242: 1982 Session-Constituent Correspondence
Series 243: 1982 Session-General Correspondence
Series 244: 1982 Session-Legislative Correspondence
Series 245: 1982 Session-Specific Bill Requests
Series 246: Unidentified Compendium of Bills
Series 247: Bateman's Pocket Appointment Books, 1964-1977
Series 248: Photograph
Series 249: Oversize and Medium Oversize Maps
Arrangement
The Herbert H. Bateman Papers consist of Bateman's state senatorial office files, 1968-1982, which are arranged alphabetically according to subjects and issues. Each subject file contains all types of materials: correspondence, memoranda, reports, publications, pamphlets, newspaper clippings, bills, and other legislative documents. The collection includes voluminous background materials on the various issues, as well as correspondence and papers revealing Bateman's positions on the issues.
The collection contains little information on Bateman's political activities (the original file inventory indicates that such material was retained) such as campaigns or party activity. The only file dealing with a political campaign is one entitled "Trible," which contains Bateman's correspondence with members of the Virginia Senate pertaining to the campaign of Representative Paul Trible for the U.S. Senate.
The Bateman Papers have been arranged almost completely according to the original office file organization. Unfortunately, maintaining original office integrity has also meant retaining serious inconsistencies and redundancies. During Bateman's 14-year tenure in the Senate, he had several legislative aides who often duplicated files under different names or placed similar material in different files. With a few exceptions, these inconsistencies have been kept in the arrangement of this collection.
Several files have been altered because the original office files had no apparent order. These files include Kepone, Ports of Virginia/Virginia Port Authority, and State Water Control Board/Water Resources. In addition, the files of Constituent Correspondence and Legislative Correspondence (originally filed alphabetically as "correspondence") have been moved to the end of the collection, and the files of Consumer Credit, Consumer Protection, and School Distribution Formula have been moved into the alphabetical file order.
Hints for Users
If users of this collection are researching Bateman's position or assembly action on a particular issue, there are several things they must do and know in order to ensure that they find all relevant materials.
First, there are several series that include materials related to many different issues. Users are advised to at least skim the following series at the beginning of the collection: Attorney General Opinions, JLARC, Legislative Proposals, Post-Session, Pre-Session, and Senate Bills. And skim these series at the end of collection: Research Materials, Constituent Correspondence, Legislative Correspondence, and 1982 Session.
Second, if users are interested in particular types of materials, such as Attorney General's opinions, bills, or constituent correspondence, be aware that, although there are separate series for them, such materials can also be found throughout the collection.
Third, materials are occasionally filed under very non-descriptive and misleading titles. The most notable of these are large amounts of material pertaining to the income tax structure of Virginia filed under Joint Subcommittee To Study Virginia's Individual Income Tax Structure, and materials pertaining to Bateman's campaign against "open" visitation in state college dormitories, filed (among other series) as Senate Joint Resolution 24 (S.J.Res. 24).
Fourth, in some cases, similar, even duplicate, material is stored in different series. Series descriptions usually indicate other series containing similar material, but, for the user's convenience, below is a list of the most severe redundancies:
Abortion, see also: Medicaid Issues
Adult Homes, see also: Elderly, Homes for Adults, Homes for the Aged, Pine Haven Adult Home, Welfare and Institutions
Coal & Energy Commission, see also: Uranium Mining
Coastal Zone Land Management Act/Bill, see also: Wetlands
Gas Tax, see also: Highway Funds, Trucks
Higher Education, see also: Senate Joint Resolution 24 (S.J.Res. 24), William and Mary, the College of (W&M)
Industrial Revenue Bonds, see also: Newport News Shipbuilding, Ports Of Virginia
Kepone, see also: Seafood Industry
Limitations on Spending, see also: Proposition 13
Metro, see also: Transportation - Northern Virginia
Newport News Downtown, see also: Peninsula Economic Development Council
Newport News Public Education, see also: Sex Education
Ports of Virginia, see also: Virginia Port Authority
Sales Tax on Vending Machines, see also: Vending Machine Taxes
Sea Grant Consortium, see also: Virginia Institute of Marine Science (VIMS)
State Water Control Board, see also: Water Resources
Fifth, for the user's convenience, the following is a partial cross-referencing of series (listed by first key words) that contain material relevant to a number of more inclusive and overarching issues and subjects:
1. Banking/Business
Banking Legislation
Bankruptcy
Insurance
Interest Rate Legislation
No-Fault Insurance
Savings And Loan Legislation
2. (State) Budget/Finance (also see Taxation) Budget
Federal Block Grant
Finance Committee
Limitations on Spending
Local Revenue Sources
Procurement Bill
Proposition 13
3. Consumers
Consumer Credit
Consumer Protect Ion
Product Liability
4. Crime And Punishment (also see Justice/Courts)
Capital Punishment
Corrections
Execution Bill
Juvenile
Law Enforcement Training
Parole
Sentencing
Sexual Assault
Spouse Abuse
5. Education/Schools
Busing
Education, Public
Education Association of Newport News
Educational Issues, 1982
Kindergarten
School Distribution Formula
Sex Education
Special Education
Virginia State School
6. Elderly
Adult Homes
Elderly
Homes for Adults
Homes for The Aged
Pine Haven Adult Home
Tax Relief for the Elderly
Welfare for the Elderly
7. Energy
Biomass
Coal Tax
Coal & Energy Commission
Fuel Conversion Authority
Uranium Mining
Virginia Electric and Power Company (VEPCO)
Virginia Oil & Gas
8. Environment
Air Pollution
Auto Inspection
Coastal Zone Land Management Act/Bill
Environment
Environmental Protection Agency
Kepone
Litter Laws
Nature Conservancy
State Water Control Board
Toxic Substances (Act)
Water Resources
Wetlands
9. Family
Abortion
Artificial Insemination
Divorce Laws
Domestic Relations Law
Habitual Offenders Law
In Vitro
Parental Support
Spouse Abuse
Wage Assignment in Support Cases
10. Health/Medical
Abortion
Artificial Insemination
Asbestos
In Vitro Laetrile
Medical Lien
Medical Malpractice
Medicaid & Health Issues
Medicaid Cost Containment
Occupational Therapist
Optometrist Legislation
Patrick Henry Hospital
Prenatal Care
Rehabilitation & Social Services
Virginia Evaluation Act
11. Higher Education
Christopher Newport College
Higher Education
Old Dominion University
Senate Joint Resolution 24 (S.J.Res. 24)
Tuition Assistance
Virginia Educational Loan Authority (VELA)
Virginia Institute of Marine Science (VIMS)
William & Mary
12. Housing
Homebuilders
Housing
Manufactured Housing Association
Virginia Housing and Development Authority (VHDA)
13. Justice Courts
Attorney General's Opinions
Court System
Courts of Justice
Intermediate Court of Appeals
Judicial Nominations
Juvenile Justice
Sentencing [By Judges]
Tort Claims
14. Labor
Labor Laws
Public Employees
Retirement
Right to Work
Unemployment Compensation
15. "Moral" Issues
Abortion
Busing
Gun Control
In Vitro
Lottery
Obscenity
Pari-Mutuel Betting
Senate Joint Resolution 24 (S.J.Res. 24)
16. Newport News/Peninsula Educational Association of Newport News
Industrial Revenue Bonds
Newport News [Several Subjects]
Peninsula [Several Subjects]
Reapportionment
Yorktown, Town of Zoning
17. Ports Industrial Revenue Bonds
Ports of Virginia
Richmond Waterfront Terminals
Tobacco Conference
Trucks
Virginia Port Authority
18. Seafood Industry
Fishing Licenses
Kepone
Marine Resources Management
Seafood Industry
Seafood Products Commission
Virginia Institute of Marine Science (VIMS)
19. Taxation
Joint Subcommittee
Sales Tax Regulation
Taxation
Taxation Procedures
Vending Machines
Watercraft Sales and Users Tax
20. Transportation/Highway
Gas Tax
Highway Appropriations
Highway Department Study
Highway Funds
Interstate 664
Metro
Pentran
Transportation
Trucks
21. Welfare
Medicaid
Rehabilitation & Social Services
Virginia Evaluation Act
Welfare & Institutions
Western State Hospital
Additional Descriptive Data
Related Material
Congressional papers from Herbert H. Bateman are also located in the Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary, but are currently unprocessed.
Index Terms
Persons:
Dalton, John N.; Godwin, Mills E. (Mills Edwin), 1914-; Holton, A. Linwood (Abner Linwood), 1923-; Robb, Charles S.
Subjects:
Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Energy policy--Virginia.; Intergovernmental fiscal relations--United States.; Education--Virginia.; Transportation--Virginia.; Public welfare-- Virginia.; Capital punishment--Virginia.; Prison sentences--United States.; Fish trade--Virginia.; Shellfish trade--Virginia.; Virginia--Politics and government.
Corporate Names:
Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company.
Geographical Names:
Newport News (Va.)--History.
Components List
  Series 1: Abortion
- Abortion, 1950-1982. (Box-folder 1:1-3)
  - Correspondence and memoranda, 1977-1981., 7 items. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Items regard Medicaid funding for abortion. Virginia State Health Department recommendation, letters from constituents and health organizations and Bateman's replies.
  - Material relating to legislation on funding for abortions, 1950-1979., 24 items. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Photocopies from Code of Virginia (1950, 1960, 1975) and of articles in law reviews. Copies of House Bill No. 502, of Bateman's proposed amendments to it, of roll call on this bill (1978), and of undated letter stating Bateman's position on it, and copy of Senate Bill No. 927 (January 1979).
  - Correspondence, clippings, pamphlets, and other items received from constituents and lobbying groups, concerning the question of state funding for abortions, 1974-1982., 82 items. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Includes sample copies of Bateman's responses (6 February 1978 and ca. February 1979) and copy of House Bill No. 541 (28 January 1982).
    See also the series on general constituent correspondence, series 237, 238, and 242; and the Medicaid series, series 113 and 114.
  Series 2: Adult (Nursing) Homes
- Correspondence, memoranda and statements regarding adult (nursing) homes, 1979-1981., 17 items. (Box-folder 1:4)
  Information collected for study of adult homes and Virginia Medical Assistance Program, 1979-1981.
  See also Elderly, series 43; Homes for Adults, series 74; Homes for the Aged, series 75; Medicaid and Health Issues, series 113; Pine Haven Home for Adults, series 146; and Welfare and Instituions, series 226.
  Series 3: Air Pollution
- Correspondence and legislative papers, relating to bill(s) to establish Air Pollution Inspection Program and 1976 amendments to Clean Air Act, February 1950-1976., 15 items. (Box-folder 1:5)
  Series 4: Artificial Insemination
- Report and cover letter concerning surrogate parenthood, 1981-1982., 2 items. (Box-folder 1:6)
  Copy of Report of the Department Welfare Study Committee on Surrogate Parenthood to the Senate Committee on Rehabilitation and Social Services and the House Committee on Health, Welfare and Institutions, 1 October 1981, with cover letter of 6 January 1982.
  Series 5: Asbestos
- Correspondence, and legal papers concerning statute of limitations on asbestos-related disease, 1980., 11 items. (Box-folder 1:7)